<!-- Various bits and pieces cut from the old docs that we don't necessarily want
in the official docs.  Keep around for awhile...  -->

<section><title>External EDP Control</title>

<p>It is possible to use Mobius to send MIDI messages to an EDP
hardware device.  Any function performed with a key, button, or MIDI
message can be redirected to the EDP instead of Mobius, or sent to
both Mobius and the EDP at the same time.  This is something I use
during testing to compare how Mobius and the EDP respond to functions.
This probably has limited practical use, but I would be curious to
know if you find one.</p>

<p>To use this feature you must first select a <i>MIDI Through</i>
device.  This must be a MIDI device to which the EDP is connected.
See the <ref>MIDI Control</ref> section for more on seleting a through 
device.</p>

<p>Next, pull down the <i>Configuration</i> menu and select the
<i>External EDP</i> item.  A dialog appears with the following
parameters.</p>

<glossary>
<gi>
<dt>MIDI Control</dt>
<dd>Controls which device will be responsive to functions initiated
by buttons, keys, or MIDI events.  A value of <i>Mobius</i>
means that only the Mobius program will receive functions, <i>EDP</i>
means that only the external EDP will receive functions, and 
a value of <i>Both</i> means, astonishingly, that both devices will
receive functions.</dd>
</gi>
<gi>
<dt>Channel</dt>
<dd>The channel on which the EDP receives MIDI messages.</dd>
</gi>
<gi>
<dt>Base Note</dt>
<dd>The first note or controller to which the EDP will respond.
This is what the EDP calls the <i>Source#</i> parameter.
</dd>
</gi>
<gi>
<dt>Controllers</dt>
<dd>When checked, the EDP responds to MIDI continuous controller
events, otherwise the EDP responds to MIDI key events.  This
is what the EDP calls the <i>ControlSource</i> parameter.</dd>
</gi>
</glossary>

<p>When triggering functions with MIDI messages, Mobius will
automatically translate the trigger message into the
message the EDP needs according to the <i>Base Note</i> and 
<i>Controllers</i> parameters.  That means you don't have to 
program a foot controller or control surface to send
contiguous note or controller messages that the EDP requires.
Mobius will convert random messages into contiguous note
or controller messages for you.</p>

</section> <!-- External EDP Control -->

