<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document>
<document>
<heading>
<title>Mobius 2.2 Release Notes</title>
<date>August 2012</date>
</heading>

<TOC/>

<section><title>Introduction</title>

<p>This document is intended for users of older Mobius releases
wishing to upgrade to Mobius 2.2. If you are not upgrading from an older
release you may skip to the 
<a href="installation.htm">Installation Guide</a>.</p>

<section><title>Upgrading from 2.1 to 2.2</title>

<p>To upgrade an existing 2.x release to 2.2, simply run the installer
and allow it to overwite the previous files.  As always, your
configuration files will be preserved, only the binary application
files will be replaced.  Review the <ref>Release Notes for version 2.2</ref>
section for the changes.</p>
</section>

<section><title>Upgrading from 1.x to 2.x</title>

<p>There were a large number of changes made in 2.0, but few of
them will be visible.  Many of these were architectural changes that
will make future enhancements easier.  Lots of small bugs were fixed
and a few host crashes were fixed.  Because of the size of the changes
we have decided to make our first change to the major release number
and call this version 2.0.  Future releases will be built on 2.0 and 
increment the minor version number, 2.1, 2.2, etc.   I do not plan any
further development of the 1.45 branch unless it is necessary to 
fix a serious bug for someone that is unable to upgrade to 2.0.</p>

<p>Unlike the 1.x releases, when you install 2.0 it will not
automatically copy and upgrade the old 1.x configuration files.  Mobius
will install into a new directory, <i>c:\Program Files\Mobius 2</i>
on Windows and <i>/Applications/Mobius 2</i> on OS X.  On OS X, the
configuration files will be stored in 
<i>/Library/Application Support/Mobius 2</i>.  Because the installation
and support directories are different, if you want to continue using your
old configuration files you will have to manually copy them from the
version 1 directory to the version 2 directory.  This will work fine for
bindings but not all of the 1.x parameters, particularly those involving
synchronization will be recognized in 2.0.  Post to the forums or send mail
to jeff@circularlabs.com if you need assistance doing the upgrade.</p>

<p>The plugins will also have different names, on Windows the VST plugin
will be shown as either "Mobius 2" or "MobiusVst2".  On OS X both the
VST and AU plugins will be shown as "Mobius 2".  Unlike past releases it
is permissible to have the old 1.45 version a and the new 2.0 version 
installed and in use at the same time.  You could for example add
a 1.45 Mobius and 2.0 Mobius to the same Bidule layout.  This is so you
can test the new version to make sure it will work properly for you without
losing the ability to go back to 1.45 if you find problems.</p>

<p>The new features that will be visible are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Redesigned synchronization engine for improved sync</li>
<li>Support for Audio Units host sync (Logic, Garageband)</li>
<li>Support for other sample rates besides 44100</li>
<li>Redesigned UI button window that works like other binding windows</li>
<li>Improved Speed, Pitch, and Time Stretch controls</li>
<li>Improved OSC support</li>
</ul>

<p>While this release has many improvements over 1.45, due to number
of changes it is quite possible that new bugs have been introduced.  We
expect to find bugs over the next few months and we will do our best
to fix them promptly.  If you are an active performing musician and do not
have time to test the new release to make sure all of your current scripts
and techniques will work the same, then I recommend that you consider this 
like a beta release and wait for one or two point release.</p>

</section> <!-- Upgrading from 1.x -->

</section> <!-- Introduction -->

<section><title>Release Notes for version 2.2</title>

<section><title>Speed Shift, Pitch Shift, and Time Stretch</title>

<p>The major new feature of this release is a redesign of the speed and pitch
functions and controls.  Of particular interest is the new <b>Speed Bend</b>
control that can be used to change the playback rate smoothly using a 
MIDI CC or pitch wheel rather than making semitone jumps.</p>

<p>Also of interest
is the <b>Time Stretch</b> control that can smoothly change the loop duration
and tempo <b>without</b> changing the pitch.  Note however that since
<i>Time Stretch</i> relies on the old pitch shifting algorithm, there
are still some remaining issues with added latency that may make it unsuitable
when synchronizing multiple loops.  We consider this a "beta" feature, but
can be be fun in some situations.</p>

<p>Many of the function and control names were changed during the
redesign.  In previous releases, changing both the playback speed and pitch
of the loop was referred to as <b>rate shift</b>.  We now consistnetly use the 
word <b>speed</b> instead of <b>rate</b>.  So parameters such as 
<i>Rate Sequence</i> are now <i>Speed Sequence</i>.  Some of the names were
not simple substitutions of "rate" and "speed".  For example the
<i>Rate Shift</i> function is now known as <i>Speed Step</i> to better indicate
that it changes speed in semitone steps.  The following tables show
how old speed and pitch function names have changed.</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Rate Shift</b> - is now <i>Speed Step</i></li>
<li><b>Rate Up</b> - is now <i>Speed Up</i></li>
<li><b>Rate Down</b> - is now <i>Speed Down</i></li>
<li><b>Rate Next</b> - is now <i>Speed Next</i></li>
<li><b>Rate Previous</b> - is now <i>Speed Previous</i></li>
<li><b>Rate Normal</b> - is now <i>Speed Cancel</i></li>
<li><b>Speed</b> - is now <i>Speed Toggle</i></li>
<li><b>Sustain Speed</b> - is now <i>Sustain Speed Toggle</i></li>
<li><b>Fullspeed</b> - is now <i>Speed Cancel</i></li>
<li><b>Halfspeed</b> - is still <i>Halfspeed</i></li>
<li><b>Pitch Shift</b> - is now <i>Pitch Step</i></li>
<li><b>Pitch Normal</b> - is now <i>Pitch Cancel</i></li>
</ul>

<p>The following track controls have been added.</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Speed Octave</b></li>
<li><b>Speed Step</b></li>
<li><b>Speed Bend</b></li>
<li><b>Pitch Octave</b></li>
<li><b>Pitch Step</b></li>
<li><b>Pitch Bend</b></li>
<li><b>Time Stretch</b></li>
</ul>

<p>The behavior of some of the functions has changed slightly, be
sure to review the 
<a href="techniques.htm#speedShift">Speed Shift</a>, 
<a href="techniques.htm#pitchShift">Pitch Shift</a>, 
<a href="techniques.htm#timeStretch">Time Stretch</a>, 
sections of the <i>Mobius Techniques</i> manual for full detals.</p>

<p>If you want to try out the new speed, pitch, and stretch controls,
a new display component has been added that allows you to organize
two sets of track controls rather than having single very tall stack
of controls.  The track controls stacks in the status area are now
called <i>Floating Track Strips</i>, see the
<a href="exploring.htm#trackStrips">Customizing the Track Strips</a>
section of the <i>Exploring Mobius</i> manual for information on adding
two independent track strips to the status area.</p>

</section> <!-- Speed and Pitch -->

</section> <!-- 2.2 Release Notes -->

<section><title>Release Notes for version 2.1</title>

<section><title>Sample Rates</title>

<p>When Mobius runs as a plugin, it will use whatever sample rate
that the host is using.  When Mobius runs standalone, you select the
sample rate in the <i>Audio Devices</i> configuration window.  The new
field labeled <i>Sample Rate</i> is the first item below the device
selection panels.  You can select one of two rates: 44100 and 48000.
Let us know if you feel you need other rates.</p>

</section> <!-- Sample Rates -->

<section><title>New Synchronization Engine</title>

<p>All of the synchronization features that exist in 1.45 still exist in 
2.0, but the way they are configured is different.  In 1.45 
synchronization was defined in the <i>preset</i>.  In 2.0 synchronization is
defined in the <i>track setup</i>.</p>

<p>The parameters you formerly saw in the <i>Synchronization</i> tab
of the <i>Preset</i> window you will now see in the <i>Synchronization</i>
tab of the <i>Track Setup</i> window.  One consequence of this is that most
synchronization parameters will be shared consistently by all tracks.</p>

<p>The majority of the synchronization options such as <i>Out Sync
Realign Action</i>, <i>Out Sync Min Tempo</i>, <i>MIDI/Host Sync
Unit</i>, and <i>Beats Per Bar</i> do not need to be different in each
track.  Having these as preset parameters raised the possibility that
each track would have a different value which complicated
synchronization decisions (and caused bugs).  Now it is easy to define
synchronization parameters consistently for all tracks.</p>

<p>There are however two sync parameters that do occasionally need to
be different in each track: <i>Sync Source</i> and <i>Track Sync Unit</i>.</p>

<p><i>Sync Source</i> is what we used to call <i>Sync Mode</i>.  It defines
the style of synchronization that will be performed by the track.  The possible
values are:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>None</b> - No synchronization</li>
<li><b>Track</b> - Synchronize with another Mobius track</li>
<li><b>Out</b> - Send MIDI clocks to other devices</li>
<li><b>MIDI</b> - Synchronize with a MIDI clock sent by another device</li>
<li><b>Host</b> - Synchronize with the beat or bar of the plugin host</li>
</ul>

<p>The default sync source for all tracks is defined with the 
<i>Default Sync Source</i> parameter under the <i>Synchronization</i>
tab of the <i>Track Setups</i> window.  If you want to change this
for selected tracks, select the <i>Tracks</i> tab of the 
<i>Track Setups</i> window and find the parameter labeled
<i>Sync Source</i>.  By default the value of this parameter is <i>Default</i>
which means the track will use the sync source defined
by the <i>Default Sync Source</i> parameter.  If you change this, the track
will follow the selected sync source and ignore the default sync source.</p>

<p>A similar parameter override exists for the <i>Track Sync Unit</i> 
parameter.  This parameter determines where the synchronization point
is when the sync source is <i>Track</i>.  The possible values are 
<i>Subcycle</i>, <i>Cycle</i>, and <i>Loop</i>.  The default sync
unit is defined with the <i>Default Track Sync Unit</i> parameter
under the <i>Synchronization</i> tab.  If you want to override this
change the <i>Track Sync Unit</i> parameter under the <i>Tracks</i> tab.</p>

<p>This is described in more detail in the 
<a href="synchronization.htm#Synchronization Parameters">Synchronization Parameters</a> section of the <i>Mobius Synchronization</i> manual.</p>

<p>In the following table we will provide a translation between the 1.45
synchronization parameters on the left and the equivalent 2.0 parameters
on the right.</p>

<glossary>
<gi><dt>Sync Mode = Off</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>None</i></dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Sync Mode = Out</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Out</i></dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Sync Mode = Out Manual Start</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Out</i> and
check the <i>Out Sync Manual Start</i> box.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Sync Mode = MIDI Beat</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>MIDI</i> and
set <i>MIDI/Host Sync Unit</i> to <i>Beat</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Sync Mode = MIDI Bar</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>MIDI</i> and
set <i>MIDI/Host Sync Unit</i> to <i>Bar</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Sync Mode = Host Beat</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Host</i> and
set <i>MIDI/Host Sync Unit</i> to <i>Beat</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Sync Mode = Host Bar</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Host</i> and
set <i>MIDI/Host Sync Unit</i> to <i>Bar</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Track Sync Mode = Off</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to anything other than <i>Track</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Track Sync Mode = Subcycle</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Track</i> and
the <i>Track Sync Unit</i> parameter to <i>Subcycle</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Track Sync Mode = Cycle</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Track</i> and
the <i>Track Sync Unit</i> parameter to <i>Cycle</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Track Sync Mode = Loop</dt>
<dd>Set the <i>Sync Source</i> parameter to <i>Track</i> and
the <i>Track Sync Unit</i> parameter to <i>Loop</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Empty Track Action</dt>
<dd>Now under the <i>Switch</i> tab of the <i>Preset</i> window.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Resize Sync Adjust</dt>
<dd>Now under the <i>Synchronization</i> tab of the <i>Track Setups</i>
window as <i>Out Sync Resize Adjust</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Speed Sync Adjust</dt>
<dd>Now under the <i>Synchronization</i> tab of the <i>Track Setups</i>
window as <i>Out Sync Speed Adjust</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Switch Sync Adjust</dt>
<dd>No parameter in 2.0, use <i>Out Sync Resize Adjust</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Mute Sync Mode</dt>
<dd>Changed to <i>Out Sync Mute Action</i>.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Out Sync Realign Mode</dt>
<dd>Changed to <i>Out Sync Realign Action</i></dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Record Beats/Bar</dt>
<dd>Changed to <i>Beats Per Bar</i></dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Minimum Tempo</dt>
<dd>Changed to <i>Out Sync Min Tempo</i></dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Maximum Tempo</dt>
<dd>Changed to <i>Out Sync Max Tempo</i></dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Auto Record Bars</dt>
<dd>Now under the <i>General</i> tab of the <i>Preset</i> window.</dd>
</gi>

<gi><dt>Auto Record Tempo</dt>
<dd>Now under the <i>General</i> tab of the <i>Preset</i> window.</dd>
</gi>

</glossary>

<p><b>NOTE:</b> It is important to understand that the 1.45 
synchronization parameters will not be automatically upgraded
when you run the 2.0 release.  You will need to manually change
synchronization parameters in 2.0.</p>

<p>Besides the synchronization parameters, many other parameters have
changed location.  Preset parameters will usually still be under the
<i>Presets</i> window, but you may need to explore the new tabs.</p>

</section> <!-- Synchronization -->

</section> <!-- 2.1 Notes -->

</document>

