<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document>
<document>
<heading>
<title>Mobius Installation Guide</title>
<date>January 2011</date>
</heading>

<TOC/>

<section><title>Introduction</title>

<!--
<P>Welcome and congratulations on your purchase of Mobius, the worlds
most powerful live-looping software!  Not only will Mobius open the
doors to new worlds of creativity heretofore only glimpsed at the edge
of a dream, but it will also make you a better person, make you lose
weight, and improve your cellular phone reception.  Don't you just
love these fawning, self-aggrandizing introductory paragraphs?  It's a
requirement I'm told.</p>
-->

<p>Welcome and thank you for your interest in Mobius, the world's most
powerful live-looping software!  If you already know what Mobius does,
you may skip ahead to the <ref>Documentation</ref> section.</p>

<p>If you're still wondering what the heck is this "looping" thing is
all about, Mobius essentially lets you to make live audio recordings
and play them back in an endless loop.  While a loop is playing you
may add to it and modify it in many ways.  One of the most common uses
for a looper is to record background parts for "one man band" solo
performers but this is just scratching the surface of what Mobius can
do.  If you would like more information on the history and evolution
of looping techniques the <a href='http://www.loopers-delight.com'>Loopers Delight</a> 
web site is the best place to explore and learn.</p>

<p>Mobius was inspired by many hardware and software loopers of the
past and present, but most of its core features can be traced to the
Gibson Echoplex Digital Pro (EDP) with Loop IV software.  Though not
technically an emulator, if you're familiar with the EDP you should
feel at home.  From a foundation of EDP features, Mobius adds multiple
tracks, chromatic pitch and rate shifting, instant loop editing,
scripting, and much more.</p>

<p>Be warned that Mobius is a complex program with an enormous number
of options.  Many people say that it is "too complicated", the user
interface is "unpolished", and the documentation "sucks".  All of these 
are true.  If you are looking for a DL-4 emulator with photo realistic
knobs you can just plug in and play then look elsewhere.  If you are
looking for a new musical instrument you can customize to work the
way <b>you</b> want it to, then you've come to the right place.  Just
be prepared to do some reading and ask a lot of questions.</p>

<p>If you decide to take the plunge, we strongly recommend you join
the <a href='http://www.circularlabs.com/forums'>Mobius Support
Forums</a>.  This is where most Mobius discussion happens.  You can
also email us at <b>jeff@circularlabs.com</b>.</p>

<p>Mobius free because it is people like you that have helped
make Mobius what is today.  All we ask is that you report bugs and
help diagnose them.  You are also encouraged to send feature requests.
We can't guarantee that we'll implement every request but just knowing
what people want to do helps us make design decisions that may make
those things possible in the future.</p>

r<p>Thank you for helping us make Mobius better!  I hope you enjoy it
as much as we do.</p>

</section> <!-- Introduction -->

<section><title>Documentation</title>

<p>Because Mobius is a complex application, the documentation has been broken
up into several parts to make it easier to digest.  The documentation
is installed with the product and is also available on the web at
the <a href="http://www.circularlabs.com/documentation/documentation.htm">Mobius Document Index</a>.</p>

<p>If you are new to Mobius,  please read at least
the <a href="starting.htm">Getting Started With Mobius</a> 
manual before you begin.  Then at least skim <a href="exploring.htm">Exploring Mobius</a> 
to become familiar with some of the more advanced features.   The other manuals
go into more depth on techniques and options, you won't need to read these
right away but you should return to them once you become more comfortable with Mobius.</p>

<ul>

<li><a href="starting.htm">Getting Started With Mobius</a> - Introduces fundamental Mobius concepts and the user interface</li>

<li><a href="exploring.htm">Exploring Mobius</a> - Explains more advanced concepts, control options, and customization</li>

<li><a href="techniques.htm">Mobius Techniques</a> - Tutorials on some of the commonly used looping functions and techniques</li>

<li><a href="synchronization.htm">Mobius Synchronization</a> - Explains how to synchronize Mobius with other devices and applications</li>

<li><a href="reference.htm">Mobius Reference</a> - A complete reference of all functions, parameters, and internal variables</li>

<li><a href="scripts.htm">Mobius Scripting</a> - Explains how to write Mobius scripts</li>

</ul>

</section> <!-- Documentation -->

<section><title>Installation</title>

<p>Read the sections <ref>Windows Installation</ref> or <ref>OS X
Installation</ref> for the installation steps specific to your
operating system.</p>

<p> If you are upgrading a previous installation, usually you just
install the new version over the previous version, all of your
previous configuration will be preserved.</p>

<p>While you can have more than one version of Mobius installed, this
is not recommended.  When Mobius runs, it reads configuration files
from a directory that is shared by all installations on the machine.
If you try to run Mobius binaries from an old version with newer
configuration files, Mobius may not work properly.  If you try to run
new Mobius binaries with older configuration files, the files may be
automatically upgraded and will no longer work with the binaries from
the older version.</p>

<section><title>Windows Installation</title>

<p>Mobius is supported on Windows XP, Vista and 7.  It is not a native
64-bit application but it is known to work on 64-bit hardware.</p>

<p>Mobius is distributed as an executable installer.  When you run the
installer it will prompt you for an installation directory.  The
default is <i>c:\Program Files\Mobius</i>.  The Mobius executables,
initial configuration files, and example files will be placed in this
directory.</p>

<p>The installer will also copy the Mobius VST plugin to the
directory <i>c:\Program Files\VstPlugins</i> which is the most
common directory for VST plugins.  If you are using a different
plugin directory you must manually copy the <i>MobiusVst.dll</i>
file from the installation directory to your plugin directory.</p>

<p><b>NOTE:</b> If you decide to move Mobius to a different directory
after installation you must reinstall, you cannot simply move or
rename the directory.  During installation an entry in the Windows
registry is created that contains the path to the installation directory.
Moving or renaming this directory will not update this registry entry,
you must run the installer again to update the registry.  If the
Mobius UI is blank or displays a lot of question marks, it usually
means that the registry does not point to the correct installation
directory.</p>

<p>All of your custom configuration settings are stored in the
installation directory in two files: <i>mobius.xml</i>
and <i>ui.xml</i>.  Unlike other applications, customizations
are <b>not</b> stored in the <i>Documents and Settings</i> directory
for your user account.  This means that if you delete the installation
directory you will lose your customizations.</p>

<p>If you wish to reinstall or upgrade, do not run the uninstaller or
delete the current installation directory.  Just install into the same
directory that was used by the previous installation.  
All of your customizations will be preserved.</p>

</section> <!-- Windows -->

<section><title>OS X Installation</title>

<p>Mobius is supported on OS X 10.4 or later.  It is a
 universal binary that  will run on both PPC and Intel machines.</p>

<p>Mobius is distributed as a disk image (dmg) file.  After downloading
it will normally mount automatically and contain a single folder named
<i>Mobius</i>.  To install simply drag this folder into the 
<i>Applications</i> folder.  After copying, open the folder and click
on the Mobius icon which looks like a blue glass sphere.</p>

<p>When Mobius is run for the first time, it creates this directory 
to hold various editable configuration files:</p>

<ul>
<li>/Library/Application Support/Mobius</li>
</ul>

<p>The primary configuration files <i>mobius.xml</i> and <i>ui.xml</i>
are stored here.  This is also commonly used for user written scripts.</p>

<p>If you wish to use the Audio Unit plugin you must manually
copy folder <i>Mobius.component</i> from the installation directory
to one of these directories:</p>

<ul>
<li>/Library/Audio/Plug-Ins/Components</li>
<li><i>&lt;your home directory></i>/Library/Audio/Plug-Ins/Components</li>
</ul>

<p>To use the VST plugin you must manually copy the <i>Mobius.vst</i>
folder from the installation directory to one of these directories:</p>

<ul>
<li>/Library/Audio/Plug-Ins/VST</li>
<li><i>&lt;your home directory></i>/Library/Audio/Plug-Ins/VST</li>
</ul>

<p>To install a new version of Mobius you simply delete or rename the
existing Mobius folder before copying the new one.  You cannot copy an
upgrade folder into an existing Mobius folder, you must replace the
existing folder.  Since the configuration files are stored in an
different folder, customizations will not be lost during an
upgrade.</p>

<p>While it is possible to have more than one version of Mobius
in the <i>Applications</i> folder this is not recommended.  Since the
Mobius configuration files are always stored in the 
<i>/Library/Application Support</i> folder, they may not be compatible with
all of the Mobius releases you have in your <i>Applications</i> folder.</p>

</section> <!-- OS X -->

</section> <!-- Installation -->

<section><title>Running Standalone Mobius</title>

<p>Even if you intend to use Mobius as a VST or Audio Units plugin, it
is recommended that you start using it as a standalone application.
Plugin host applications add a another layer of complexity to the
setup process, when you are just getting started it can be difficult
to tell whether a problem is caused by Mobius or the host application.
There are also some user interface customizations that can only be
performed in the standalone Mobius window.  Once standalone Mobius has
been configured and is working properly, you can advance to using the
plugin.  The <ref>Mobius Plugin</ref> section discusses this in more
detail.</p>

<p>To run standalone Mobius you must configure audio devices, this is
described in the <ref>Audio Device Configuration</ref> section.</p>

<p>Most people will also want to configure one or more MIDI devices
such as footswitches or control surfaces.  This is described in
the <ref>MIDI Device Configuration</ref> section.</p>

<p>On Windows, you run Mobius by selecting the Mobius item with the
blue orb icon from the start menu, or by running <i>mobius.exe</i>
from the command line.</p>

<p>On OS X, you run Mobius by clicking the application icon from the
<i>Mobius</i> folder inside the <i>Applications</i> folder.</p>

<p>After running Mobius you should be greeted with a window that looks
similar to this:</p>

<img alt='Initial Layout' src='images/installation-initial.gif'/>

</section> <!-- Running Standalone -->

<section><title>Audio Device Configuration</title>

<p>Using standalone Mobius requires the selection of an audio device.
If you do not select a device you can still do things like arranging
and resizing the user interface or creating function bindings, but
Mobius can't be used for looping.  Pressing buttons in the UI or
sending MIDI commands will have no effect, Mobius will appear to be
frozen.</p>

<p>When you select an audio device it is important to choose one with
low latency.  Latency is a complex topic covered in more detail in the
<ref>Tuning Latency</ref> section.  For now you can think of it as the
amount of time it takes to get an audio signal from an input channel
of an audio device, through the computer, and back to an output
channel of an audio device.  Mobius can compensate for latency in some
cases so it is still quite usable regardless of which device you
choose.  But with high latency devices you may hear "skips" or "lag"
in the sound when you do certain things.</p>

<p>To get low latency you will usually have to buy an aftermarket
audio interface rather than using the one that came bundled with your
computer.  External Firewire or USB interfaces are recommended.  If
you have a laptop, PCMCIA cards can work well. There are many choices
in aftermarket audio interfaces, some work better than others.  You
will need to do some research and ask questions on forums to find the
one that works best for you.  But generally speaking the so called
"integrated" audio interfaces that came with the computer do not
perform well.  They can be fine when you're just getting started but
if you want to use Mobius for serious live performance, almost
everyone buys a professional audio interface.</p>

<p>To configure an audio device, start standalone Mobius, open
the <i>Configuration</i> menu and select the <i>Audio Devices</i>
item.</p>

<p>If you use OS X, you will see two selection panels, one labeled
<i>Input Device</i> and one labeled <i>Output Device</i>.  Normally
you select the same device for both input and output but this is not
required.  On OS X you are always using a <i>Core Audio</i> device
driver which will usually have low latency.</p>

<image src='images/installation-audio-osx.gif'
       caption='OS X Audio Device Configuration Window'/>

<p>If you use Windows, life is a bit more complicated.  There are
three selection panels, one labeled <i>ASIO Devices</i>, one labeled
<i>Input Device</i> and one labeled <i>Output Device</i>.  You
should always select an ASIO device if one is available as these have
the lowest latency.  An ASIO device will provide both inputs and
outputs so you only need to make one selection.</p>

<image src='images/installation-audio-windows.gif'
       caption='PC Audio Device Configuration Window'/>

<p>If you do not have any ASIO devices on Windows, you may select an
<i>MME</i> device.  You must select one device from the <i>Input
Device</i> panel and one device from the <i>Output Device</i> panel.
If you have more than one audio device, normally you will select the
same one for both input and output.  MME devices tend to have very
high latency, they are fine for exploring Mobius features but are not
recommended for serious use.</p>

<p>At the bottom of the dialog you will see a set of fields with
labels <i>Suggested Latency Milliseconds</i>, <i>Override Input
Latency Frames</i>, and <i>Override Output Latency Frames</i>.  Leave
all of these fields empty.  Do not press the Calibrate Latency
button.  Once Mobius is configured and working properly, read the
<ref>Tuning Latency</ref> section for more information about
optimizing latency for your system.</p>

<p>Once you have selected an audio device click the <i>Ok</i> button
to close the window.</p>

<section><title>Audio Device Recommendations</title>
</section>

</section> <!-- Audio Device Configuration -->

<section><title>The First Loop</title>

<p>Connect an instrument or microphone to the input channels of the
audio device.  Mobius operates in stereo so it always uses audio
device channels in stereo pairs called "ports".  By default Mobius
always uses the first input and output port.  If you have an audio
interface with more than one pair of stereo channels, Port 1 is
usually channels 1 and 2, port 2 would be channels 3 and 4 etc.</p>

<p>Check the level meters on the audio interface to make sure that a
signal from your instrument is being received.  External Firewire and
USB devices usually have a software "mixer" application, make sure the
fader levels on all channels have been raised.</p>

<p>Run Mobius and play something on your instrument.  In the center of
the Mobius window is a thin rectangle called the <i>audio meter</i>
you should see it flicker as you play your instrument.  If you do not
see any movement in the Mobius window try connecting your instrument
to a different set of input channels on the audio interface.  If your
interface has channels on both the front and back, it may be unclear
which ones are 1 and 2.  If you've tried sending a signal through all
of the devices inputs and you still see nothing flickering in the
Mobius window, post a message on the forum and we will try to
help.</p>

<p>If you see that lovely audio meter flicker, click the button labeled
<i>Record</i> at the top of the Mobius window.  You should see some
numbers in the center of the window changing.  Play something on your
instrument, then click the <i>Record</i> button again.  What you
recorded should start playing back in an endless loop.  If you don't
hear anything, make sure you have speakers or headphones connected to
the first pair of output channels on your audio device.  If you have a
device with multiple channels try connecting speakers to all of the
other channels.  If you still don't hear anything, post a message on
the forum.</p>

<p>If you hear your first loop playing, congratulations!  If you hear
some "clicks" or "pops" while the loop is playing there are two
common explanations.  The first is that the instrument level is
too high and you are having digital "clipping".  Try lowering the 
instrument level and try again.  Clicks can also happen when the
default latency setting for your audio device is too low.  Read the
<ref>Tuning Latency</ref> section to learn how to raise the latency.</p>

<p><b>NOTE:</b> One common error when setting up a software looper is
having the audio output of the looper feed back into the input.  For
example, it is common to have several sound sources connected to a
mixer, then have the mixer output connected to the input of the audio 
device.  If the output of the audio device is also connected to the mixer,
you can have feedback.  When Mobius is overdubbing, anything that is
currently playing may then be included in the overdub (with a slight
delay).  The loop will become increasingly louder and sound
"metallic".</p>

<p>If the output of the audio device is connected directly to the
speakers this should not be a problem.  If you are using a mixer, you
will have to find a way to exclude the channel containing the audio
device output from the "bus" being sent to the audio device input.  If
you are familiar with Mackie mixers, <i>Mute Alt 3-4</i> combined with
<i>Control Room Source</i> buttons can accomplish this nicely.</p>

</section> <!-- The First Loop -->

<section><title>MIDI Device Configuration</title>

<p>While you can control Mobius using the computer keyboard or
clicking buttons in the window, most people control Mobius with a MIDI
device such as a footswitch or a control surface.  Footswitches are
widely used because they allow the musician to keep both hands on
their instrument.  Control surfaces with rows of faders and knobs are
very convenient for setting track levels and adjusting feedback.</p>

<p>Mobius can also send messages to other devices using MIDI.  The
most common use for this is to send MIDI clock pulses to a drum
machine or sequencer so that drum patterns or pre-recorded
accompaniment tracks can be played in sync with the Mobius loop.</p>

<p>You can use any device that sends MIDI commands to control Mobius.
Many newer MIDI devices will connect to the computer though a USB
port.  For devices that only support connection with a MIDI cable, you
will also need to buy a MIDI interface for your computer.  See the
<ref>MIDI Device Recommendations</ref> section for more information on
buying MIDI interfaces and devices.</p>

<image src='images/installation-midi.gif'
       caption='MIDI Device Configuration Window'/>

<p>To configure MIDI devices open the <i>Configuration</i> menu
and select the <i>MIDI Devices</i> item.  There are two columns of
device selection panels, the panels on the left select devices to be
used when Mobius runs as a standalone application, the panels on the
right select devices to be used when Mobius runs as a plugin.  If you
have MIDI devices that connect directly to the computer using a USB
cable, the names you see should be similar to the name of the device
like "Korg nanoKontrol".  If you have MIDI devices that connect with
MIDI cables to an external MIDI interface, the names you see will be
usually be numbered port names like "Some Device Port 1", "Some Device
Port 2", etc.  When using MIDI interfaces make sure you select the
same port that your MIDI device is connected to.</p>

<p>When selecting devices it is important to select only the ones that
you really need.  You can select as many input devices as you want,
but if Mobius will only be receiving commands from one of
them it will waste time looking at messages from the
others.  If you run Mobius as a plugin, it is <b>very important</b>
that you only select devices that are not also being opened by the
host application.  If both Mobius and the host try to use the same
device this can cause problems like commands being performed twice,
and in some cases even crashes.  Selecting MIDI devices for the
Mobius plugin is rare, you usually let the host manage the MIDI
devices and have it route MIDI into and out of the plugin.  This is
discussed in more detail in the <ref>Mobius Plugin</ref> section.</p>

<p><i>Input Devices</i> are selected if you want to receive MIDI
commands to control Mobius.  When you run Mobius standalone you almost
always select at least one input device.  When you run Mobius as a
plugin you almost never select an input device.  Instead you let the
plugin host manage the MIDI devices and you let the host route MIDI
into and out of Mobius.</p>

<p><i>Output Devices</i> are selected if you want Mobius to send
messages to another hardware device or plugin.  The most common use
for this is to send MIDI clock pulses to a drum machine or sequencer.
Using scripts it is also possible to send any MIDI message to another
device to do things like changing patches or triggering samples.  If
you are running Mobius as a plugin, selecting an output device is
common in one special case: sending MIDI sync pulses through a
"loopback" device to control the tempo of the host application.  This
is discussed in more detail in the <ref>Mobius Plugin</ref> section.
If you are not intending to send MIDI pulses to another device or to
the host application, you normally will not select an output
device.</p>

<p><i>Through Devices</i> are selected if you want to send a copy of
the MIDI message received from the input devices to other devices.  This
is relatively uncommon, but you might want to use this if the
footswitch can send commands to both Mobius and something else, and
you don't have a MIDI splitter.  All MIDI messages received by the
input devices are simply sent immediately to all the through devices.</p>

<section><title>MIDI Device Recommendations</title>

<p>First determine whether you need a MIDI interface.  You will need a
MIDI interface if you want to control Mobius using a footswitch,
keyboard, or other MIDI device that can only connect with MIDI cables.
You will also need a MIDI interface if you want to <i>send</i> MIDI
commands to a drum machine or other device that can only be connected
with MIDI cables.  If all of the devices you want to use can connect
directly to the computer with USB cables, then you do not need a MIDI
interface.</p>

<p>If you do need a MIDI interface, there many relatively inexpensive
ones available.  Unlike audio interfaces, MIDI interfaces are not very
complicated and almost anything from a reputable brand will work fine.
The simplest interfaces will little more than a cable with a pair of
MIDI in/out connectors on one side, a USB connector on the other and a
"lump" in the middle.  Larger interfaces will support more than one
input and output port.  If you only need to use the MIDI interface
with Mobius a simple "1 by 1" interface is enough.  Popular brands
include M-Audio, E-MU, and MOTU.  Before you by a MIDI interface
though, check to see if your audio interface also includes one.  Many
audio interfaces also include a 1x1 MIDI interface.</p>

<p>Probably the most asked question regarding MIDI devices is "what's
the best MIDI footswitch"?  Unfortunately there isn't a very large
selection of MIDI footswitches and most are rather expensive.  By far
the most popular MIDI footswitch used with Mobius is the <b>Behringer
FCB-1010</b>.  In many ways it is the ideal footswitch: it sends note on
and off messages, it has "banks" so you can assign up to 100 Mobius
commands to switches, and it has two integrated expression pedals to
control track level and feedback, and at $150 USD it is among the
least expensive footswitches available.  The problem many people have
with it is that it is large.  It takes up a lot of floor space and
dragging it to gigs can be inconvenient.  There are smaller
footswitches available but most of them cost several times more.  If
you are new to MIDI and are unsure of what would be best for you post
a message to the forum and we'll try to help.</p>

<p>When you look for footswitches there are two important things to
consider: does it support "momentary" switches and does it support
"banks".  A momentary switch is one that sends a MIDI message when you
press it and also when you release it.  Some switches will send note
messages (Note On when pressed Note Off when released) and some will
send continuous control messages (CC greater than zero when pressed
and CC zero when released), both of these types can be used with
Mobius.  While you can do basic looping without momentary switches, if
you want to use some of the more advanced features like "sustain
functions" or "long press behavior" you will need momentary switches.
Many of the cheapest footswitches were designed for keyboard players
to select patches and they only send MIDI program change messages.
Switches that only send program changes are not momentary.</p>

<p>The concept of "banks" is common but manufacturers call it by
different names.  A bank is basically a set of MIDI messages assigned
to each switch and different banks can cause the switches to send
different MIDI messages.  For example bank 0 of the popular FCB-1010
might send MIDI note numbers 0 through 9, bank 1 would send note
numbers 10 through 11, etc.  Banks are important because there are
literally hundreds of things in Mobius that could be assigned to a
MIDI message.  With footswitches that don't have banks, you will be
limited to a small number of things you can control with your feet.
Footswitches that support banks typically have a set of "up" and
"down" switches to scroll through the banks.  The FCB-1010 has 10
banks of 10 switches allowing you to send 100 different Mobius
commands.</p>

<p>There are other footswitches that work great with Mobius and are
relatively small such as the <i>GORDIUS Little Giant</i> and the
<i>Rocktron All Access</i>.  Unfortunately they are several times more
expensive than the FCB-1010, but if money is less important than size,
definitely check those out.</p>

<p>A control surface is typically a device that tries to emulate a
mixer track strip, usually with a fader and one or more rotary knobs
for each track.  While we don't think these are as essential as a
footswitch, they are very nice for adjusting Mobius track output
levels, input levels, pan, and feedback.  There are many choices here
that vary greatly in size and features.  The Korg Nano series are
inexpensive and small.  The Novation Remote series combines a control
surface with a keyboard which is handy for chromatic pitch shifting.
Behringer, Mackie, M-Audio and AKAI all make interesting control
surfaces.  If you aren't sure what you need we recommend you first
spend some time learning what you can do with Mobius tracks, then look
for the controller that meets your needs.  As usual, forums are a good
source for reviews and advice.</p>

</section> <!-- MIDI Recommendations -->

</section> <!-- MIDI Device Configuration -->

<section><title>Other Control Options</title>

<p>It is also possible to control most Mobius functions using the
computer keyboard.  The keys are "momentary" switches so they can be
used for sustain functions and long-press behavior.  If you're
exploring Mobius for the first time and aren't sure if you want to
invest money in a footswitch, a cheap alternative is to buy any USB
keyboard, pry most of the keys off, then step on the ones that remain.
This is obviously not a very durable option for live performance, but
it does work.</p>

<p>Mobius also supports the Open Sound Control (OSC) protocol, with
default support for the <i>TouchOSC</i> application that runs in the
Apple iPhone and iTouch devices.  This is an advanced topic that is
not yet fully documented.  If you are interested in OSC post a message
on the forums or send me email.</p>

</section> <!-- Other Control Options -->

<section><title>Mobius Plugin</title>

<p>On Windows, Mobius may be used as a VST plugin.  On OS X Mobius may
be used as either a VST plugin or an Audio Units plugin.  Be sure to
read the <ref>Installation</ref> section and make sure the plugin
files have been copied to a place that will be seen by your host
application.</p>

<p>Host applications vary widely in how they deal with plugins.  Even
hosts that operate in similar ways may use different terminology when
talking about plugins.  This makes it difficult to write a
comprehensive document on using the Mobius plugin.  We will give you
some general guidelines and go into some detail on a few popular
hosts, but it is simply not possible to document how to use Mobius in
every host application.  If you have never used a plugin with your
host before, try starting with a simple plugin like a digital delay or
soft synth to become familiar which using plugins in your host.</p>

<p>Mobius is an unusual plugin.  Most plugins fit into one of two
categories, they are either <i>effects</i> or <i>synths</i>.  Typical
effects plugins are compressors, filters, and reverbs.  They receive
audio, and send out processed audio, and they don't support MIDI
control.  A synth plugin normally receives MIDI events, sends out
audio, but does not receive audio for processing.</p>

<p>Mobius is like a combination of an effect and a synth.  It needs to
receive and send audio like an effect, but it also needs to receive
MIDI events like a synth.  Many hosts, particularly older DAWs, have
trouble with this.  They either can't support the dual nature of the
Mobius plugin, or they require complicated configuration to make the
necessary connections.</p>

<p>Mobius is also unusual in that it supports 16 input and output
channels or "pins".  The vast majority of effects plugins only support
a single set of stereo input and output channels.  Some hosts will
simply refuse to load Mobius because it has more than 2 channels.
Others will load it but will only let you access the first 2
channels.</p>

<p>Some hosts do not let effects plugins have direct access to MIDI
devices.  Instead they control plugins only through "parameter
automation".  In this style of host, the plugin advertises a set of
parameters that may be controlled by the host.  The host then allows
the user to set up associations between MIDI events and these
parameters.  In this situation, you have to configure the Mobius
functions and parameters to make available to the host.  Then you
do all of your MIDI mappings in the host.  While this works it
can be difficult to set up, and the host may not support parameters
that behave like "momentary buttons" which will prevent you from using
some Mobius features.</p>

<p>Then there is synchronization.  Mobius is also unusual in that it
tries to provide synchronization of loop recording with the host's
transport controls if it has them.  Unfortunately hosts differ
radically in how they implement the horrible VST specification, so
trying to get synchronization to work on a new host is almost always
a problem.</p>

<p>If this is starting to sound scary, unfortunately it is.  There are
several popular hosts that work well for Mobius and we try to support
them whenever they have a new release.  But we simply cannot guarantee
that Mobius will work with every host out there, and we don't have the
resources to even try.  If you have a problem with your favorite host
and are willing to spend some time with us to diagnose them, we may be
able to work with you.  But otherwise you will have to consider one of
the recommended hosts.</p>

<section><title>Recommended Hosts</title>

<p>In our experience, plugin hosts come in roughly four varieties.</p>

<ol>
<li><b>Recorders</b> - typical digital audio workstations</li>
<li><b>Arrangers</b> - oriented toward arranging short audio clips in loops and sequences</li>
<li><b>Racks</b> - simulates a rack of synth and effect hardware</li>
<li><b>Modular</b> - a "boxes and wires" graphical user interface</li>
</ol>

<p>The <i>Recorder</i> style is familiar to most people.  These are
the traditional DAWs that have a user interface organized like a
multi-track tape recorder.  Examples of this style include <i>Cockos
Reaper</i>, <i>Cakewalk Sonar</i>, <i>Steinberg Cubase</i>,
and <i>Apple Logic</i>.  They excel at recording, mixing, and
non real-time editing.  While they are widely known they are not always
good hosts for Mobius.  They often have a hard time dealing with
effects that need both MIDI and audio inputs and they may not support
plugins that have many channels.  Generally they are designed for
studio use rather than real-time performance.  We try to make an effort
to support Reaper and Logic, support for the others will be
spotty.</p>

<p>The <i>Arranger</i> style is usually designed more for live
performance.  Here the focus is on arranging pre-recorded samples or
recording short samples of a fixed length and applying effects to them
in real time.  Examples of this style include <i>Ableton Live</i>,
<i>Sony ACID</i>, <i>Apple Garage Band</i>, and <i>FL Studio</i>.  These
often have many of the same problems as the Recorder-style hosts
but they can be better.  Of these, <i>Ableton Live</i> 
is an outstanding host for Mobius and is actively supported.</p>

<p>The <i>Rack</i> hosts attempt to simulate a hardware rack of
effects and synths and most do not provide audio recording and
editing.  They are oriented toward "always on" plugins that are
constantly responding to MIDI and audio in real time.  Examples of
this style include <i>Apple Mainstage</i>, <i>Audiofile Engineering
RAX</i>, and <i>Brainspawn Forte</i>.  These can be good hosts for
Mobius but they are relatively unusual among the current user base so
support may be spotty.  Of these, we actively support <i>Apple
Mainstage</i>.</p>

<p>The <i>Modular</i> hosts typically present a user interface that
uses pictures to represent plugins and other devices, and lets you
draw "wires" to connect them.  Examples of this style
include <i>Plogue Bidule</i>, <i>AudioMulch</i>, <i>Usine</i>,
and <i>Max/MSP</i>.  Modular hosts are well suited for Mobius because
they make it easy to visualize all of the input and output channels
and make connections to them.  They excel at creating "patches"
combining effects and synths controlled by MIDI.  They typically are
not as easy to use for traditional linear audio and MIDI recording and
editing.  We use and recommend <i>Bidule</i>
and <i>AudioMulch</i>.</p>

</section> <!-- Recommended Hosts -->

<section><title>Plugin Insertion</title>

<p>On Windows the installer will copy the Mobius VST plugin to the
directory <i>c:\Program Files\VstPlugins</i> which is the most common
directory for VST plugins.  If your host can be configured to load
plugins from more than one directory, make sure <i>VstPlugins</i> is
on the list.  If the host must load plugins from a different directory
you must manually copy the <i>MobiusVst.dll</i> file from the
installation directory to your plugin directory.  You only need to
copy that one .dll file, leave all the other files in the installation
directory.</p>

<p>Once the plugin files have been copied to the proper directory, the
Mobius plugin should appear in the host application.  Where this
appears will be different in every host.  The VST plugin may be named
either "Mobius" or "MobiusVst".  The AU plugin should be named
"Mobius".  Some hosts organize plugins by the manufacturer name so
there may be an item named "Circular Labs" you need to expand to see
the plugin.  If you do not see the plugin you may need to ask the host
to "rescan" the plugin directory.</p>

<p>If your host has the concept of <i>tracks</i> and you have a choice
between inserting Mobius in an audio track or a MIDI track, you
usually want to insert it in an audio track, then arrange to have MIDI
routed to that track.</p>

</section> <!-- Plugin Insertion -->

<section><title>Plugin Pins</title>

<p>Some hosts may refuse to load plugins that have more than one pair
of stereo input and output channels, by default Mobius has 8 pairs of
stereo channels.  If the host will not the insert the Mobius plugin,
try reducing the number of channels.</p>

<p>Run standalone Mobius, bring up the <i>Global Parameters</i>
dialog, select the <i>Limits</i> tab and find the parameter
named <i>Plugin Ports</i>.  Change this parameter value to <i>1</i>,
click <i>Ok</i>, and close standalone Mobius.  Now run the host
application again, ask it to rescan plugins, and try inserting the
Mobius plugin.  Whether this works or not please post a message with
your results on the forums or send us email.  We are interested in
compiling a list of those hosts that require this workaround.</p>

<p>If the host does support multi-channel plugins then you have the
option of having each Mobius track receive from and send to different
channels.  Mobius organizes channels into stereo pairs called "ports".
Each track may be configured to have one input port and one output
port.</p>

<p>Assigning tracks to ports provides several useful performance
options, such as having some tracks take input from a soft-synth
rather than live audio.  You may also insert a different effects
plugin after the output of each track, making each track sound
different even though they are driven by the same input signal.</p>

<p>This is described in more detail in the <i>Track Setups</i> section
of the <i>Getting Started</i> manual.</p>

</section>

<section><title>Dual Window Mode</title>

<p>Unlike most VST plugins, Mobius by default opens two windows when
running under a <i>Microsoft</i> operating system.  The first is a
small window containing the Mobius icon and the text
<i>Click to open Mobius window</i>.  The second is the main Mobius window.</p>

<p>The first small window is the normal "editor" window created by the
VST host.  Most plugins put all of their user interface in this
window.  This window does however have some limitations for Mobius
users.  First, the window cannot be resized so if you change the
layout of the Mobius user interface it may not be possible to display
everything.  A more serious limitation is that computer keyboard key
events are often not passed along to he plugins so you cannot use the
keyboard to control Mobius.</p>

<p>Because of these limitations, by default Mobius opens a second
window over which it has complete control.  This window may be resized
and will receive keyboard events just like the standalone Mobius
window.  If you close the main window, the VST editor window will
remain open, simply click anywhere inside the editor window to reopen
the main window.  If you close the editor window, both windows will be
closed.</p>

<p>Some people prefer to have Mobius put the user interface into to
the VST editor window.  This is possible if you are willing to live
with the limitations.  Bring up the <i>Global Parameters</i> dialog,
find the parameter named <i>Dual Plugin Edit Window</i>, and uncheck
the checkbox.  Close the both the Mobius main window and the editor
window and ask the host to reopen the editor window.  You may need to
restart the host application for this change to take effect.</p>

<p>We have had reports of crashes using single window mode with some
hosts.  The causes for this are unclear, but if you are experiencing
crashes using the plugin in single window mode, try enabling dual
window mode.</p>

<p>Dual window mode cannot be enabled in the Mac Audio Unit plugin.</p>

<p>Dual window mode may be enabled in the Mac VST plugin but it is not
the default.</p>

</section> <!-- Dual Window Mode -->

<section><title>Plugin MIDI Devices</title>

<p>Mobius normally receives MIDI events directly from the VST host so
it is not usually necessary to select MIDI input or output devices for
the plugin.  If at all possible you should try to arrange to let the
 host manage the MIDI devices and route MIDI events into Mobius.</p>

<p>There are two special circumstances where you might want the Mobius
plugin to open it's own MIDI devices:</p>

<ol>
<li>The host is unable to route MIDI events to an "effects" plugin</li>
<li>You want Mobius to generate a master MIDI clock to synchronize the host</li>
</ol>

<p>The first case used to be rare and only seen on very old hosts, but
it is unfortunately becoming more common in modern hosts like
Mainstage.  The philosophy coming into vogue is that plugins shouldn't
have to know anything at all about MIDI, they should get all of their
control signals through <i>plugin parameters</i>.  It is then the hosts
job to associate a MIDI event with each plugin parameter.  This works
fine for your typical effects plugin with a dozen or so parameters, but
Mobius literally has hundreds of parameters.  Further some Mobius
features like pitch and rate shift are meant to be controlled using
MIDI notes like a synthesizer.</p>

<p>It is possible to control almost everything using plugin parameters
if necessary, this is described in the <ref>Plugin Parameters</ref>
section.  But depending on the host it may be more convenient just to
let Mobius open a private MIDI device connected directly to your
footswitch or control surface.  To select a MIDI input device open
the <i>MIDI Devices</i> dialog and find the device selector
labeled <i>Plugin Input Devices</i>.  Select the device that is
connected to your MIDI controller.</p>

<p>Note that some hosts may already be in control of the devices you
select in Mobius, this can cause conflicts and in some cases crashes.
If you select a MIDI device for the Mobius plugin you should configure
the host so that it does <b>not</b> open the same device.  Usually
there will be a dialog where you can pick which MIDI input and output
devices the host will use.  Unfortunately some hosts simply open every
available MIDI device.</p>

<p>The other common reason to have the plugin open a MIDI device is to
send master MIDI clocks to the host.  Plugins cannot normally be the
sync master for the host, but this is possible if the plugin can
generate MIDI clocks sent to a "loopback" device.  This is discussed
in more detail in the <i>Synchronization</i> section of the
<i>Getting Started</i> manual.</p>

<p>While it is possible to select a <i>Plugin Through Device</i> in
the <i>MIDI Devices</i> window, we are not aware of an interesting use for
this.  If you find one let us know!</p>

</section> <!-- Plugin MIDI Devices -->

<section><title>Plugin Parameters</title>

<p>Most plugins support <i>parameters</i> which can be controlled by
the host.  Common examples are output level, delay time, or filter
curve.  Some hosts support <i>parameter automation</i> where a
sequence of parameter values can be programmed to change in time with
an audio or MIDI track.</p>

<p>Mobius is unusual because it has hundreds of parameters.  These
include the continuous controls like <i>Input Level</i>
and <i>Pan</i>, preset parameters like <i>Loop Count</i>
and <i>Quantize</i>, and functions like <i>Record</i>
and <i>Reset</i>.  Each of these parameters can be further scoped to a
particular track or track group.</p>

<p>Because most hosts do not deal well with plugins that have more
than a few dozen parameters, you must explicitly select the parameters
to expose to the host.  The default set of plugin parameters is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Input Level</li>
<li>Output Level</li>
<li>Feedback</li>
<li>Secondary Feedback</li>
<li>Pan</li>
<li>Selected Track</li>
<li>Quantize Mode</li>
<li>Switch Quantize</li>
</ul>

<p>You may declare additional parameters in the <i>Plugin
Parameters</i> dialog from the <i>Configuration</i> menu.
The <a href='exploring.htm#Plugin Parameter Bindings'>Plugin Parameter Bindings</a>
section of the <a href='exploring.htm'>Exploring Mobius</a> manual
has more information on configuring plugin parameters.</p>

<p>As mentioned in the <ref>Plugin MIDI Devices</ref> section, some
hosts only allow plugins to be controlled through parameters, direct
access to MIDI events is not possible.  For these hosts you can either
configure Mobius to open a private MIDI device, or you can declare all
of the functions you want to use as plugin parameters, and associate
them with MIDI events in the host.</p>

<p>Binding MIDI events with plugin parameters is complex and different
in every host.  If you are not familiar with this process, the best thing
to do is post questions on the forum.</p>

</section>

<section><title>VST Patches</title>

<p>Most VST plugins support the notion of a "programs" or "patches"
which are selectable from a open menu in the editor window.  Mobius
does not support the VST patch menu.  Changing Mobius operating behavior
is done through popup menus in the main Mobius user interface.</p>

</section> <!-- VST Patches -->

<section><title>Bypass</title>

<p>It is important to note that when a plugin is bypassed that
no audio is "flowing" through the plugin.  Without a steady stream
of audio flowing through the plugin the Mobius user interface
will appear to be hung.  If you need to silence the Mobius plugin
yet still have it be responsive to keyboard or MIDI commands,
you will need to use Mobius functions such as <i>Reset</i>
or <i>Mute</i> rather than bypassing the plugin.</p>

</section> <!-- Bypass -->

<section><title>Audio Input Monitoring</title>

<p>If you are processing the audio signal from your instrument through
an effects plugin before sending it into Mobius, it is common to want
to monitor your signal "through the computer" rather than with a "side
chain bus".  Monitoring your instrument while you loop is a complex
topic that will not be explored fully here.  The main thing to
understand is that if you play something on your instrument, you see
the Mobius input level meter flickering, but you don't hear anything,
you may need to enable input monitoring in Mobius.</p>

<p>Bring up the <i>Global Parameters</i> dialog and find the parameter
named <i>Monitor Audio Input</i>.  Check the checkbox and
click <i>Ok</i>.  If you can now hear your instrument then you are
monitoring "through the computer".  This means that you will hear the
effects that all the plugins in the chain, including Mobius, are
having on your signal.  This is a perfectly fine way to monitor but it
has consequences, primarily that you may hear a <i>latency delay</i>
between the time you do something on your instrument and you hear the
processed sound.</p>

<p>The alternative is to use some form of side chain monitoring,
typically this is done with a hardware mixer outside the computer or
with audio interfaces that support "zero latency monitoring".</p>

<p>If your instrument is a MIDI controller, or if you are guitar
player using an amp modeling plugin then you have little choice but to
monitor through the computer since it is the plugins that are defining
the sound of the instrument you want to monitor.  If you are using
external hardware go generate the sound you want to monitor, it is
best to do side chain monitoring to avoid the latency delay.</p>

<p>Something to be aware of is that when you have the <i>Monitor Audio
Input</i> option checked, the sound you are hearing might have a
"metallic" quality that sounds like "flanging".  If you hear this it
often means that there is some form of chain monitoring active that is
being combined with the through-the-computer monitoring.  Because the
through-the-computer signal will be slightly delayed, when combined
with the side chain it will sound very much like a flanging effect is
being applied.  In this case you either need to disable the side chain
monitoring, or uncheck Monitor Audio Input.</p>

<p>Also when you monitor through the computer, you normally want to
disable Mobius latency compensation.  Rather than have Mobius do the
compensation, you are already compensating mentally by adjusting your
playing technique by playing slightly "ahead".  The reasons for this
are complicated and discussed more in the <ref>Tuning Latency</ref>
section.</p>

</section> <!-- Audio Input Monitoring -->

<section><title>Plugin Audio Devices and Latency Compensation</title>

<p>Audio devices selected for Mobius in standalone mode will not be
opened when running as a VST.  The VST host must open the audio
devices and route them to Mobius.</p>

<p>The input and output latency override values are however still used
when Mobius runs as a plugin.  When you are just getting started and
intend to use Mobius primarily as a plugin, it is recommended that you
do not set latency overrides and instead let the host give Mobius the
input and output latency.</p>

<p>If you do want to switch between plugin and standalone Mobius you
will want to configure Mobius to use the same buffer size as you use
in the plugin host application so the latency overrides will
match.</p>

<p>Unfortunately because Mobius configures latency using milliseconds
rather than buffer sizes it can be difficult to know how Mobius
latency compares to the host.  As a general rule, a buffer size of 256
is the same as 5 milliseconds.  So a buffer size of 512 would
correspond to 10 milliseconds, 128 would correspond to 2 milliseconds,
etc.</p>

<p>Again, it is best initially to simply make sure that the two
latency override values are empty or set to zero.  Latency calibration
is covered in more detail in the <ref>Tuning Latency</ref>
section.</p>

</section> <!-- Plugin Audio Devices -->

</section> <!-- Mobius Plugin -->

<section><title>Tuning Latency</title>

<p>Latency compensation is a complex topic and we recommend that you
not be obsessed with it when you are just getting started.  If you are
using an ASIO or Core Audio device driver, latency is so small that
many people don't even notice it.  For those new to looping, timing
problems with the loop start and end points or the alignment of
overdubs are more often due to footswitch technique than latency.</p>

<p>If you feel you need to fine tune latency compensation you can go
through the calibration process described in this section.  Typically
people use the latency calibration dialog to find the starting values,
then manually tweak latency overrides by ear until they sound
right.</p>

<p>A common misconception is that latency is a fixed quality of a
particular audio interface.  If you buy audio interface <i>X</i> you
will have low latency, but audio interface <i>Z</i> will have high
latency.  The brand of audio interface certainly has an effect on
latency but there are many other factors that determine the minimum
latency you can achieve.  These include the speed of the CPU, the
amount of memory, the firewire chipset, shared memory in the graphics
card, wireless network adapters, and the other software you have
running.  Latency isn't something you can just add up based on your
hardware and software.  It is something you
<b>tune</b> to be as small as possible without causing audio distortion.</p>

<p>Tuning latency is similar to finding the maximum comfortable
operating speed of a car.  It may be possible to drive your car at 120
MPH but it may be noisy and hard to control at that speed.  Setting
latency too low is like driving a car too fast.  You are putting
demands on the computer that it may not be able to meet reliably.
Raising latency is like slowing down your car, it may take longer to
do some things but you'll arrive safely.</p>

<p>The consequence of having latency too low is that you will "miss an
interrupt" or have "buffer underrun".  The audio device is constantly 
asking the computer for little blocks of audio to play.  If the 
computer cannot respond in time the audio interface will leave a gap 
in the digital audio stream, this will sound like a harsh "click" or "pop".  
Raising latency gives the computer more time to respond to requests from 
the audio device so these audible glitches don't happen.</p>

<p>Because looping is to a large degree delayed playback of previously
recorded material, latency is actually much less of an issue than in
an application like a virtual instrument.  Latency is noticeable
whenever an abrupt change in playback occurs, such as ending the
initial recording, and unquantized functions such as loop switch, loop
trigger, or trim.  If you are "quantizing" functions, you may not
hear any glitches because quantizing will delay the function long enough
that we can compensate for latency.</p>

<p>When you make an abrupt change, say a loop switch, Mobius will
already have buffered some frames from the current loop.  We
can start buffering frames from the next loop, but they will be
delayed a few milliseconds while we play the frames that are already
in the buffer.  What output latency compensation does is begin
buffering the next loop not from the first frame, but at an offset
equal to the number of frames from the old loop that are already
buffered.  The bad effect is that a small portion of the front of the
next loop will be skipped.  The good effect is that when the next loop
finally becomes audible, it will be at its proper playback position,
the same position it would be in if there were zero latency.  This is
important if you are playing rhythmically and want the rhythm to be
maintained during the switch.  Without this there would be a few
milliseconds of "extra time" inserted whenever you switch that is
likely to annoy your drummer.</p>

<p>When you are quantizing, Mobius is usually able to anticipate where
the change in output buffering needs to occur so that the switch
occurs seamlessly without loss.  This early buffering of the next loop
can cause an audible glitch if you cancel the switch (or change the
target loop) very close to the point where the switch is scheduled.
If we have already started buffering the next loop, a few milliseconds
of it will still be heard before hearing the correct loop.  In
practice this should be a relatively rare problem as most people don't
change their mind about which loop to trigger a few milliseconds before
the trigger is to be performed.</p>

<p>Latency compensation must also be performed to ensure that overdubs
are aligned properly with the audio that was being heard during the
overdub.  Without compensation the overdub may sound slightly ahead of
or slightly behind where it should be.</p>

<p>Mobius uses information returned by the device to estimate the
amount of latency compensation to be performed.  This can be
calculated with reasonable accuracy by knowing the number and size of
the buffers used by the audio device driver.  But there are other
factors besides buffer size that contribute to latency, so sometimes
the estimate is not correct and latency must be adjustment manually.</p>

<p>At the bottom of the <i>Audio Devices...</i> dialog, there are two
fields labeled <i>Override Input Latency Frames</i> and <i>Override
Output Latency Frames</i>.  After you select a device and reopen the
dialog, the default latency adjustment values are shown to the right
of these fields.  If you enter a number into either field, it will
override the default value.</p>

<p>The easiest way to determine what these values should be is to
perform a calibration.  Click the <i>Calibrate Latency</i> button and another
dialog will popup with information about the calibration process.  In
order to calibrate, you must physically connect the left or right
output channel of the sound card to the left input channel of the same
card.  For most cards this can be done with a cable that has mini-plugs
on both ends.  If the sound card output is being sent to a mixer, you
probably have a way to connect the output to the input in the mixer.
This is called a <i>loop back connection</i>.</p>

<p>Once you have made a loop back connection, click the <i>Start</i>
button on the calibration dialog.  If you are monitoring the sound
card's output, you will hear a series of clicks.  If the loop back
connection is not correct, after about 10 seconds a message dialog
will popup saying that calibration timed out waiting for an input
signal.  If this happens check your connections and try the
calibration again.  If the calibration was successful, a
message dialog will pop up displaying the total measured latency, and
the recommended values for input and output latency frames.  Click the
<i>Accept</i> button to copy these values into the latency fields of
the Audio Devices dialog, or click <i>Cancel</i> to keep the current
values.</p>

<p>If you want to tweak the latency values manually, start by
increasing the values for both latencies by 10 until it sounds right.
You normally shouldn't have to add more than a few hundred frames.  If
it is still way out of alignment, stop adding to the input latency and
start making more radical adjustments to the output latency, up or
down in increments of 500.  If that is required, submit a bug report
with information about your computer and sound card.</p>

<p>To get a better understanding of what these values mean, you can
think that at any moment in time Mobius is receiving sound that was
performed a few milliseconds in the past, and is playing sound that
will be heard a few milliseconds in the future.  Input latency is the
number of frames it takes a sound to "get into" Mobius.  If you set
input latency too low, you will be recording sound that was performed
<i>before</i> the time you triggered the record function.  If you
set input latency too high, you will lose some of the sound immediately
after you triggered the record function.  It is more critical that
input latency be correct because miscalibration can result in unwanted
sound or loss of sound at the record start point.  If an overdub sounds
like it has the right content but isn't aligned properly, then adjust
output latency not input latency.</p>

<p>If you set output latency too low, overdubs will sound like they
are playing too late.  If output latency is too high, overdubs will
sound like they are playing too early.  Deliberately adjusting output
latency too low can actually be useful to compensate for
<i>monitoring latency</i>.  If you perform live using monitor speakers
some distance away, it will take a noticeable amount of time for the
sound to travel from the speakers to your ears. If you are overdubbing
to this sound, it may not be aligned properly on playback.  Raising
output latency can help bring the overdubs back into alignment.</p>

</section> <!-- Tuning Latency -->

<section><title>Next Steps</title>

<p>If you have been able to install and configure Mobius and record
your first loop, proceed to the <a href="starting.htm">Getting
Started</a> manual for more depth on the user interface and an
introduction to the most common looping functions.</p>

</section> <!-- Next Steps -->

<!--
<section><title>Acknowledgements</title>
</section>
-->

</document>

